Preliminary Inventory of the American Educational Research Association Records
Hoover Institution Archives
American Educational Research Association records,
1965-2000
86040
Hoover Institution Archives
103 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (45.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, statistics, and sound recordings, relating to education and educational research activities in the United States.
American Educational Research Association.
Access
Collection is open for research. Box 79 may not be used without permission of the American Educational Research Association. Collection is stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Administrative History
American association for the promotion of educational research.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, statistics, and sound recordings, relating to education and educational research activities in the United States.
Education--Research.; Education--United States.; Education.; United States.
- American Educational Research Association (AERA) (Box 1)
  - Annual meeting, New York, 1982
  - Application of research to educational practice - Correspondence
  - Awards Committee
  - Budget
  - Central Office staff
  - Committees
    - Appointments
    - Work
  - Council meetings minutes
    - 1981-1982
    - 1982-1983
  - Descriptive data
  - Government and Professional Liaison (GPL)
  - Outstanding Book Award
- American Educational Research Journal ( AERJ)
  - Correspondence, 1984
  - Editor
- Ballots
- Besag's forum
- AERA (Box 2)
  - Editor-At-Large program
  - Governance Task Force
  - Government and Professional Liaison (GPL) - Memoranda
- College Entrance Examination Board (CEEB) - Computer Science
- Computer conference
- Council for Educational Development and Research (CEDaR)
- Educational Researcher
  - Editorial board
  - Special issue (Bickel)
- Federation of Behavioral, Psychological, and Cognitive Sciences
- AERA (Box 3)
  - Annual meeting, Montreal, - Minutes, letters, 1983 April 11-15
  - National Institute of Education (NIE) - Comments
  - People interested in serving on different committees - Letters
  - President's reception
  - Presidential appointments
  - Professional Liaison Committee
- National Academy of Education - List of members, 1982 October 4
- NIE
  - Hearings, 1981 June 18
  - Justiz, Manuel - Letters
  - Lab and center competition for NIE funding Relations
- Organization of Institutional Affiliates (OIA) - Policy meetings
- Task Force - Evaluation of educational research
- AERA (Box 4)
  - Guidelines for eliminating race and sex bias in educational research evaluation
  - Testimony, 1982 May 6
- American Psychological Association (APA) - Committee on Psychological Tests and Assessment
- NIE research plan for fiscal year, 1984
- Publications
- Schneider Joe - Memoranda
- Scientific Freedom and Human Rights Committee
- Scientific Institute for Public Information
- State and Regional Educational Research Associations
- Women and minorities
- AERA (Box 5)
  - General
  - Annual report of the Committee on Critical Reviews
  - Association of American Publishers (AAP) - Award Committee
  - Book of readings
  - Cooley, William, President - Correspondence
  - Educational Researcher - Reviews
  - GPL - Information
  - Increment, 1987 August
  - President-Elect
  - Presidential appointments, 1982-1983
  - Requests for payment forms
  - Symposium, New Orleans, 1984
- NIE - Memoranda
- AERA (Box 6)
  - Annual meetings (phonotape cassettes)
  - Conferences (phonotape cassettes) (Box 7-8)
    - 1984
    - 1985 (Box 9-10)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 11)
    - 1986 (Box 12-13)
    - 1987 (Box 14-16)
    - 1988 (Box 17-19)
  - Annual meetings (Box 20)
    - - Registration forms, 1988-1989
    - - Calls for proposals, 1989-1990
    - - Award presentation and Presidential Address brochures, 1990
  - Ballots, 1989-1990
  - Childcare subsidy application, unaffiliated group space request
  - Division H committee responsibility handbook, 1990 June
  - Exhibit invitations, 1987-1991
  - Minutes of meetings, 1988 February 5 - 1990 June 1
  - Professional Development and Training - Proposal outlines
  - Special Interest Group (SIG)
    - Annual directory, 1989-1990
    - Handbook, and, 1989-1990 1990-1991
    - Research focus on black education
- NIE
  - Experimental Program for Opportunities in Advanced Study and Research in Education - Application for project support
    Scope and Contents note
    (2 folders)
  - Grant proposal material
    - Minorities and Women’s Program Grants Competition
    - Minority research (Box 21)
      (3 folders)
    - Minority research (Box 22)
    - Proposal development workshop - Questionnaires
- AERA (Box 23)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - 1981-1985
      - Council
      - Executive Board
    - - Publications Committee, Boston, 1990 April 18
  - Conference, 1978 (Box 24)
    (video tapes)
  - Increment, 1991 August
  - Annual meetings (Box 25-27)
    (phonotape cassettes)
    - 1981 April 13-17
    - 1981 April 13-17 (Box 28)
      (Los Angeles)
    - 1982
    - 1982 (Box 29)
    - 1989 (Box 30-32)
    - 1990 (Box 33-35)
    - 1991 (Box 36-38)
  - Video tapes (Box 39)
  - Phonotape cassettes (Box 40)
  - Ad Hoc committees (Box 41)
    - Long Range Planning - Final report, 1984 January
    - Relations of Research to Practice
  - Center for the Study of Teachers and Teaching in the School Context - Investigation
  - Council meetings - Minutes
    - Washington, 1987 June 2-3 1988
    - San Francisco, 1989 March 27-31
  - Cultural Tradition and Contemporary Education - International conference, Hong Kong, 1988 October 13-18
  - Educational Testing Committee - Standards for educational and psychological testing
  - Executive Board and Council - Letters and memoranda
  - GPL
  - LaValle bill
  - New Educational Researcher - Evaluation
  - Office of Educational Research and Improvement (OERI) - Center directors
  - Publications
  - General - Financial reports, minutes, letters, etc. (Box 42)
  - Executive Board meetings - Agenda, minutes, reports
    - Tucson, Arizona, 1987 October 25-26
    - New Orleans, Louisiana, 1988 April 5-9
      (annual meeting)
    - , Washington, D.C., 1988 June 6-7
    - , Boulder, Colorado, 1988 September 30 - October 1
    - , Santa Barbara, California, 1989 January 20-21
  - Notebook
  - Annual meeting programs, 1991-1993 (Box 43)
- Grant material
  - Papers prepared for the AERA project "Research Contributions for Educational Improvement,", 1984 November
  - Reports, drafts, proposals, articles
- AERA - Publications Committee minutes, 1979-1993 (Box 44)
- Educational Resources Information Center (ERIC) System
  - General
  - Clearinghouses
- Federal Education Data Acquisition Council (FEDAC)
- General Education Provisions Act (GEPA)
- Paperwork, 1980
- Reading Research and Education Center - Application for cooperative agreements
- United States. Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW) - Consulting contracts and evaluations
- AERA - Grant applications and related material (Box 45)
- United States. Office of Management and Budget (OMB) - Circular A-C1 (indirect costs)
- AERA (Box 46)
  - International Reading Association (IRA) press conference, 1981
  - Material related to a public forum for contemporary research on reading comprehension
- Center for the Study of Reading (CSR) - Reading education reports
- Dropout issues - Papers
- Curriculum reform (Box 47)
- Grants
  - Advisory Board
    - General
    - Meeting, - Minutes, 1984 April 4-6
  - Annual meeting, Chicago, Illinois, 1985 March 31 - April 2
    - Information
    - Session forms
  - Authors
  - Correspondence
  - Equity
    - General
    - Cusick, McDill, Hamilton
  - Grant timeline
  - Items for agenda, and related material
  - Kaplan, George
  - Project budget
  - Study groups
    - Calendar
    - Nominations
  - Study panel
  - Teachers - McLaughlin, Schlechty
  - Teachers/Teaching meeting panel
  - The nation's educational issues
    - General
    - Abstract
      (original and copies)
- Committee on Federal Contracting Practices (CFCP) - Papers (Box 48)
- Educational research - Copies of different manuscript announcements and microfiche of manuscripts related to educational research
- Educational research on privacy, protection of human subjects, freedom of information, and forms clearance
- Ethics
  - Grants awarded by the Ethics and Values in Science and Technology (EVIST) program, 1978
  - Research papers related to ethical issues in education
- Standards for educational evaluation - Draft
- Teachers - Teaching
- United States. Office of Management and Budget (OMB) - Circular A-122 revision
- AERA - Ethics (Box 49)
- Censorship ethics - Release of research reports
- Council for Applied Social Research Inc. (CASR)
- Family educational rights and privacy act
- Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) - Confidentiality
- Hatch amendment - Pupil rights
- National Commission on Research
- Research on privacy
- United States. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit - Peter H. Forsham v. Patricia Roberta Harris
- The Belmont Report, "Ethical Principles and Guidelines for the Protection of Human Subject of Research" (Box 50)
- Federal Education Data Acquisition Council (FEDAC)
- Human research subject
- Protection of research subjects
- Appropriations and revised budget for fiscal year, and administration budget request for fiscal year, 1981 1982 (Box 51)
- External advice and peer review in the Office of Educational Research and Improvement (OERI)
- Federal Education Data Acquisision Council (FEDAC) - Interim procedures, 1979
- Governmental and Professional Liaison of the AERA (GPL)
  - Action agenda, 1980
  - Committee meeting, 1979 October 18
  - Guide for communicating with Congress, 1980
  - Guidelines, 1979
  - Issues list, 1979 October
  - Operations, 1979 January 18
  - Operations, Description of
  - Protection of human research subject, - Proposed regulations, 1979 October
  - Youth Act of, Title II - Statement to U.S. Senate., 1980
    - Committee on Labor and Human Resources, 1980 June
- Hufstedler reception, 1980 February 13
- Letter to president Jimmy Carter
- Paperwork - Forms clearance
- Paperwork policies - Paper
- Researcher confidentiality - Press issues
- Statement on truth in testing - H.R. 4949 and H.R. 3564
- Statements presented to Congress, 1979
- Synthesis of invited papers, 1985 September
- United States. Department of Education
  - Establishment of Office of Educational Research and Improvement (OERI) - Transition recommendations, 1980
  - Personnel profile
  - Recommended nominations, 1979
  - Research and related activities in fiscal year - Federal budget, 1981 1980
    - General
    - Revised, 1980 March 31
- United States. Department of Health, Education and Welfare (DHEW) - Statement on research and development in the educational division for fiscal year, 1980
- Working coalition for Educational Research (ER) and the National Institute of Education (NIE)
- GPL (Box 52)
  - Action plan, 1978-1979
  - Chronological files
    - 1979
      - January - June
      - July - December
    - 1980
      - January - June
      - July - December
    - 1981 January - June
  - OERI - History
- Organization of Institutional Affiliates (OIA)
  - Agenda, list, 1985
  - Correspondence, 1985
  - Handouts
    - Includes correspondence, 1984
    - 1985
- United States. Department of Education
  - Assistant Secretary for Educational Research and Improvement (AS/ERI) - Profile, 1979
  - Options, 1979
  - Organization act, 1979
- Forum on Testing Practices Executive Committee, 1985-1986 (Box 53)
- GPL
  - Annual reports
    - 1983-1984
    - 1984 June
  - Committee meeting minutes
    - 1984 October 21-22
    - 1985 September 21-22
    - 1986 January 16-17
  - Old budgets
- OIA
  - General
    - 1979
    - 1980
    - 1981
    - 1982
  - Agenda, list
    - 1983
    - 1984
  - Correspondence, 1983
  - Handouts, 1983
  - Meeting minutes
    - 1979 September 16-18
    - 1980 September 28-30
    - 1981 October 21-23
    - 1982 September 19-21
    - 1983 September 18-20
- AERA (Box 54)
  - Annual meeting, 1984
  - Press conference, 1981 November 16
- GPL
  - General, 1984
  - Action agenda
    - 1980
    - 1981
  - Budgets (GPL-OIA)
    - 1981-1982
    - 1982-1983
  - Chronological files, 1989
    - March
    - April
    - May
    - June
    - July
    - August
    - September
    - October
    - November
    - December
  - Committee report, 1984-1985
  - Guiding principles and working assumptions, 1982
  - Meeting minutes
    - 1980
      - April 9 - Educational R&D Leaders, Boston
      - November 20-21 - Committee
    - , November 20-21 - Committee, 1981
    - , November 9-10 - Committee, 1982
  - Memoranda
  - Plan, 1983-1985
- GPL (Box 55)
  - Chronological files
    - 1981 July-December
    - 1982
      - January-June
      - July-December
    - 1983
      - January-June
      - July-December
    - 1984 (Box 56)
      - January-June
      - July-December
    - 1985
    - 1986
      - January-March
      - April-June
      - July-September
      - October-December
    - 1987 (Box 57)
      - January-March
      - April-June
      - July-September
      - October-December
    - 1988 (Box 58)
    - 1989
      - January
      - February
- Phonotape cassettes
- Phonotape cassettes (Box 59-61)
- AERA (Box 61)
  - Council handbook, 1995
  - Division A, 1992 April - 1994 April
- AERA (Box 62)
  - Council meeting minutes
    - 1987 April 20
    - 1994 June 11
  - Financial statements and auditors' reports
    - 1977 June 30
    - 1978 June 30
    - 1979 June 30
    - 1980 June 30
    - and, 1981 June 30 1980
    - 1981 June
    - and, 1982 June 30 1981
- Annual meeting handbook, 1995
- Clark Subcommittee on Publication Policies
- Educational Researcher study, 1972-1973
- Minorities handbook, 1994-1995
- Professional development and training handbook, 1995
- AERA - Standing Committee on the Role and Status of Women in Educational Research and Development (CRSW), History of Noddings, Nel - Papers (Box 63)
- Special Interest Groups (SIG)
  - Learning environments study
  - Regional research associations
  - Special education research
  - Subject matter knowledge and conceptual change
  - Teacher and student cognitions
  - Vocational education
- Instructional evaluations (Box 64)
- SIG
  - Critical issues in curriculum
  - Instructional supervision
  - John Dewey Society
  - Rasch Measurement
  - Religion and education
  - Research on the gifted and talented
  - Research on women and education
  - Second language
- AERA (Box 65)
  - Archives
    - Divisions
    - A - Files, 1987-1990
    - D - Measurement and research methodology
    - H - School evaluation and program development
    - I - Education in the professions
    - J - Postsecondary education
- SIG
  - Annual reports
    - General, 1989-1990
    - Association Council
  - Creation and utilization of curriculum knowledge
  - Critical examination of race, ethnicity, class and gender in education
  - Education statisticians
  - Families as educators
  - Information technology and library resources
- SIG (Box 66)
  - C's forms
  - Committee reports
  - Files
    - 1990-1991
    - 1993-1994
- AERA (Box 67)
  - Annual meeting agenda, San Francisco, - Basic Research in Reading and Literacy, 1995 April 18-22
  - Committee on the Role and Status of Minorities in Research and Development (CRSMRD)
- SIG
  - Fiscal issues, policy and education finance reports
    - 1992
    - 1993
    - 1994
  - Newsletters and publications
    - December 10
    - Measurement Services
    - Monitor
    - Psychophysiology and Education
- Phonotape cassettes (Box 68-70)
- AERA - Committee on the Role and Status of Women in Educational Research and Development (CRSW) (Box 71)
- Monitor
- SIG - Fiscal issues, policy and education finance
  - Papers
  - Report "School Issues in the States and Provinces,", 1995
- AERA (Box 72)
  - Annual meeting, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1994 April 4-8
  - Affirmative Action resolution
  - Annual reports, action agenda
- CRSW
  - Advisory Committee minutes
  - Brochures
- Educational Researcher - Annual reports, 1974-1995
- Minutes and agendas, 1989-1991
- Budgets
  - 1976-1989 (Box 73)
  - 1990
  - 1993-1995
- Childcare information
- CRSW - Correspondence
  - 1982-1985
  - (Gwyneth Boodoo), 1989-1990
- AERA - Guidelines for eliminating race and sex bias in educational research and evaluation (Box 74)
- CRSW
  - Correspondence
    - (Gwyneth Boodoo), 1991-1992
    - 1992-1995
  - History paper
- Division liaisons
- Equity research agenda, 1985
- Federation of Organizations for Professional Women
- Government and Professional Liaison Program
- The Hospitality Suite
- Liaisons to Special Interest Groups (SIG) and divisions
- CRSW (Box 75)
  - Liaisons with outside committees
  - Mailing lists
  - Meeting packets
  - Member responsibilities
  - Member survey, 1984
  - Mentoring, 1991
  - Mid-year meeting packets, 1992-1994
  - Minutes
    - 1981-1985
    - 1986-1991
    - 1992-1995 (Box 76)
- National Coalition for Women and Girls in Education (NCWGE), 1988-1989
- Office of Educational Research and Improvement (OERI) - Correspondence
- Program committee retreat
- Program session sheets for annual meetings
  - and, 1983 1984
  - 1985
  - 1986
  - 1987
  - 1988 (Box 77)
  - 1989
  - 1990
  - - Sex equity in education, 1990
  - 1991
  - and, 1992 1995
- Publications
- Role and status of minorities
- Roster recommendations, 1990-1991
- AERA (Box 78)
  - Strand 7
    (Proposal review)
  - Summary of annual meeting, 1990
- CRSW - Reviewing the Proposal Review Process
- Goodsell, Willystine - Award
- SIG - Research on Women in Education (RWE)
  - General
  - Conference, 1985
- Status of educational researchers survey, 1982 February
- Women educators
- AERA - Strand 7 study - Raw data (Box 79)
- Phonotape cassettes (Box 80-86)
- Correspondence (Box 86)
- Task Force on the Role and Future of Minorities
- AERA (Box 87)
  - Business meeting, 1996
  - Council meetings agenda
    - 1995 April 18
    - 1996
    - April 8
    - June 1-2
  - Division F budget
    - 1995-1996
    - 1996-1997
- GPL material - Strategic planning
- Roll Call issue (newspaper of Capitol Hill) - Letters, memoranda
- Strategic Planning Task Force (SPTF) - Meetings agenda
  - 1996
    - November
    - December
  - 1997 September 18
    (Goal 6: Recruitment and Preparation Issues, Mentoring, Tenure and Promotion)
- AERA - Council meetings agenda (Box 88)
  - 1995 June 24-25
  - 1997 January 24-26
- SPTF
  - Final report and material
  - Meetings agenda
    - 1996
      - February 29
      - September
      - November
    - 1997
      - April
      - October
        (final meeting)
- AERA - Council (Box 89)
  - Handbooks
  - Meetings agenda
    - 1996 January 13-14
      (New York)
    - 1997 March 24
      (Chicago)
- GPL - Committee meeting, Chicago, - Background materials, 1997 March 25
- AERA (Box 90)
  - Annual meeting Committee
  - Archivist - Correspondence
  - Center for Comparative Studies in Race and Ethnicity conference - Racial Dynamics in Colleges and Universities
  - Committee on the Role and Status of Minorities in Educational Research and Development
  - Committee on SIGs
  - Divisions
    - A - Affirmative Action Committee
    - G - Dissertation Research Award
  - Publications Committee
  - Research Policy and Practice Committee
  - Standing Committees members
  - Strategic Committee
  - Survey Committee
  - Miscellany
- CRSWRD - Committee members
- Equity officer
- GPL - Committee members
- Letters to Chairs
- Minority Task Force report
- Ombudsperson
  (Equity Officer)
- Professional development and training
- Research Consensus Panel
- AERA (Box 91)
  - Award committees
    - Cattell Early Career Award
    - Distinguished Contributions to Educational Research
    - Linquist Award
    - Palmer O. Johnson Memorial Award
    - Minority Fellowship Selection
    - Nominating
    - Outstanding Book Award
    - Presidential Award -, 1998
    - Professional Outreach Liaison
    - Publications - General
    - Relating Research to Practice Award
    - Research Priorities
    - Research Review Award
    - Telecommunication
  - Council meetings agenda, 1998
    - January 30
    - January 31 - February 1
    - June 20-21
- AERA (Box 92)
  - General
    - Bracey, Gerald W. - Case
  - Cattell Award Review Committee
  - Committee on International Relations
  - Divisions - Newsletters
  - Presidents list
- Educational Reseacher
  - Appointments and rejections
  - Curricula vitae, letters, etc.
- Encyclopedia of Educational Research (EER) Publications
- Committee - Appointments
- Federation of Behavioral, Psychological, and Cognitive Sciences
- Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics (JEBS)
  - Management Committee
  - Nominations
- Review of Research in Education - Editorial appointments
- Rudner, Larry - Case
- American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education (AACTE) (Box 93)
- AERA
  - Annual meeting, San Diego, 1998 April 13-17
    - Advertisement
    - Budget, 1998
    - Budget request
    - Conference theme ("Diversity and Citizenship in Multicultural Societies")
    - Correspondence
    - Executive Committee conference re a joint meeting of the Minorities Task Force and the AERA Minorities Standing Committee
    - Keynote speakers
    - Program - Correspondence
    - Program Committee - Correspondence
    - Speakers - Program, 1998
    - Tape information
    - "Thank you" letters to different lecturers
  - Award committee appointments
  - Council meeting, - Correspondence, 1997 May 31-June 1
  - E-mail addresses
  - Executive Board meeting, 1998 June 19
  - Phone cards information
  - Testing Practices Committee
  - Testing Standards Revision Committee
  - Web page
- Ballot
  - Biographical data for 1997 AERA nominees
  - California Anti-Bilingual Ballot
- Board agenda
  - 1997 October
  - 1998 January
- Donmoyer, Robert - Correspondence
- Letters re AERA presidential address tapes
- Letters re International Reading Association conference, in Orlando, Florida, 1998 May 3-8
- National Association for Bilingual Education (NABE) conference, 1998 February 27
- National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education (NCATE)
  - Appointments, resignations
  - Board of Examiners Representatives
- Peterson, Penelope L. - Correspondence
- President's budget
- Presidential gift
- AERA (Box 94)
  - Correspondence
    - General
    - Standing Committees
  - Council directory, 1998-1999
  - Council meeting notes and minutes
    - and, 1996 January 13-14 April 8
    - 1998 January 31 - February 1
      (New Orleans)
  - Joint Committee meeting minutes
  - Manual - Board and Council actions
  - Membership application forms
  - Membership information
    (brochures)
- Arts Education Partnership - Correspondence
- Cattell Award Review Committee - Cattell Early Career Award
- Correspondence
  - William J. Russell and James A. Banks
  - James A. Bank and Alan H. Schoenfeld
- External relations
- Governance manual,; request for payment forms; draft budget summary, 1997-1998 1997
- Governance Task Force
- Oregon. Department of Justice - Application of the Charitable Trust and Corporation Act
- Reimbursement forms
- Russell, William J. - Sabbatical leave